hey push students let's cover everything
you need for period
two before we start print out the free
speed review sheet to help you follow
along with this video it's free and you
can find the link in the description
below right now look at unit 2 Circle in
people events vocab things that you
might not quite remember that you need
to focus on as we review what you're
confident that you've mastered a topic
you can check it off and move on to the
next all right here we go like we talked
about in unit one the spish colonized
Central and South America and the
Caribbean they mined silver and
established sugar plantations and
exploited the labor of Natives and
Africa the Spanish Monarch heavily
controlled new span and forced Catholic
conversion on the natives they said
mostly male conquistadors who often
intermarried with native women the
French on the other hand focused on
finding the Northwest Passage and
waterways like the great lakes in the
Mississippi River New France spanned
from Canada down to Louisiana but was
sparsely populated they had trade
relations with the natives too which
were much friendlier than other
colonizers like the Spanish they were
also Catholic and S Jesuit missionaries
like the French the Dutch also focused
on the Northwest Passage establishing
the colony of New Amsterdam they also
traded with natives but were not as
focused on religious conversion or
subjugation finally the English
settlement in families and sought
permanent settlements the English
enjoyed greater freedom from the crown
were religiously diverse and had a great
degree of social Mobility English
population also grew quickly which
caused conflict with Native Americans
next let's look at the British colonial
regions first at Chesapeake which
included Virginia and Maryland the first
British settlers arrived at Jamestown
seeking profit they were funded by a
joint stock company and After
experiencing multiple setbacks leaders
like John Smith and John RF helped the
colony Thrive they made massive profits
by growing tobacco and plantations which
will lead to the growth of the planter
class and a reliance on slave labor the
first elected legislative body called
the house of burges was founded in
Virginia in 1619 and will serve as an
example of colonial government going
forward Maryland was founded as a refuge
for Catholics by Lord Baltimore like
Virginia its economy was based on
Tobacco farming and slave labor Maryland
also passed the Act of Toleration which
guaranteed religious freedom for all
Christians next is New England which
includes Massachusetts Rhode Island
Connecticut and New Hampshire the first
settlers in New England were pilgrims
who arrived at Plymouth they signed the
Mayflower contract establishing
self-government for the colony Plymouth
was eventually absorbed into the
Massachusetts Bay colon John Winthrop
was its first governor and described The
Colony as a city upon a hill a model
religious community the Puritans were
extremely strict and Roger Williams and
and hutchon were exiled for challenging
religious and political leaders also the
infamous Salem Witchcraft Trials took
place in the colony highlighting the
tensions and superstitions of the time
education was highly valued in
Massachusetts Bay and the economy was
based on trade and lumbering those that
were exiled from Massachusetts Bay often
went to Rhode Island which was founded
on the premise of religious tolerance
next the middle colonies of Pennsylvania
Delaware New York and New Jersey
Pennsylvania was a proprietary colony
founded by William pent a Quaker who
believed in religious tolerance friendly
relations with Natives and oppos slavery
Pennsylvania was economically diverse
and known as the Bread Basket because
they grew crops like wheat and barley
the middle colonies were also ethnically
diverse attracting German and Scots
Irish immigrants finally the southern
colonies included North Carolina South
Carolina and Georgia North Carolina was
characterized by small independent Farms
but South Carolina had lucrative rice
and indigo plantations a Reliance on
slave labor and a large Port City in
Charleston the last colony to be founded
was Georgia by James oglethorp The
Colony served as a buffer colony to to
protect the British colonist from
Spanish Florida next let's talk about
trade the British colonies were founded
according to the theory of merkus where
a country becomes Wealthy by exporting
more than it has to import under this
Theory the British colonies became part
of a trade Network known as the
Triangular Trade that took place between
Europe Africa and the Americas to better
control colonial trade the crown passed
a series of Navigation Acts but these
were rarely enforced in a policy known
as salutary neglect the colonists
enjoyed this economic freedom and made
personal profit through smuggling next
Labor in the colonies the first laborers
in the British colonies were indentured
servants these laborers agreed to work
for an individual who would pay their
way and they were usually contracted for
between 7 and 10 years the first African
laborers arrived on the coast of
Virginia in 1619 Beacon's Rebellion
aided in the switch to African slave
labor as Nathaniel Bacon LED an uprising
of landless whites against Virginia
Governor William Berkeley as the number
of enslaved laborers increased slave
codes were often passed especially in
colonies where the slave population was
high but enslaved workers attempted to
fight back by breaking tools faking
illness and even Revolt one example was
the Stono Rebellion in South Carolina in
1739 which was the largest slave
insruction in the 13 colon is resulting
in the tightening of slave coats next
Native American conflicts differences
over culture and land use led to
frequent and violent conflicts between
British settlers in Native America first
remember the potin uprising that
occurred in 1622 in the Virginia colony
when a new chief of the potin
Confederacy took over he believed war
between the two groups was inevitable
resulting in attacks on English
settlements along the James River King
Philips war was one of the deadliest
conflicts between Natives and British
settlers and eventually led to the end
of resistance of natives in New England
another conflict that occurred was the
quo Revolt which happened between the
Spanish settlers and the American
Southwest in the pbl finally the
religious movement called the Great
Awakening the first Great Awakening was
a religious revival that occurred in the
American colonies during the 1730s and
1740s caused in part because of a drop
in church attendance and Jonathan
Edwards surmon sinners in the hands of
an Angry God another leader George
Whitefield traveled throughout the
Colones preaching to huge crowds at
events called camp meetings the first
grade awakening applied to all people
regardless of their socioeconomic status
but it also created divisions between
the old lights who resisted the Revival
and the new lights who embraced it
leading to the formation of new
denominations like the Baptist and
Methodist churches the Great Awakening
had a huge impact on colonial society as
it led to separation from the church of
England and encourag colonists to
question British Authority so come exam
day what question should you be able to
answer for causes focus on causes and
effects of the system of mercantilism
and the Triangular tradeit especially on
the culture of the colonists and make
sure that you focus on the causes of
British colonization some were profit
motivated but others were motivated by
religious freedom finally you could be
asked about the effects of the first
grade awakening especially how it helped
encourage colonists to question British
Authority also for continuity and change
focus on the changes that took place
after bacon Rebellion like the switch to
using slave labor over indentured
servants finally for comparison
questions asking to compare the
colonizers or to compare the British
colonial regions appear here all over
the exam check out the aush ultimate
review packet for more help we've got
timeline study guides and Essay help
follow the link in the description below
to get a free preview and if you think
this video was helpful like And
subscribe thanks for
watching